So what exactly is periodic motion?
Periodic motion is motion that repeats
itself or that oscillates back and
forth. Some good examples of periodic
motion and simple harmonic motion is the
mass spring system and also the simple
pendulum. But let's talk about the mass
spring system. So let's say this is the
wall and we have a spring connected to a
mass horizontally
and let's say that this is the
equilibrium position of the spring.
So the spring has been stretched towards
the right.
So that means we're applying a force
to pull it towards the right to stretch
it from its equilibrium position.
As we pull it towards the right,
there is another force that wants to
push it back towards its equilibrium
position. This is known as the restoring
force.
Now once you let go,
the spring is going to move back towards
the left. Now it's not going to stop at
the equilibrium position.
It's going to move past it.
And once that happens,
it's going to bounce back the other
direction.
So it's going to move back and forth
towards the left and towards the right
and as it oscillates back and forth
you have simple harmonic motion or
periodic motion.
Now according to Hook's law the
restoring force
is equal to
* K * X.
X
is the distance measured from the
equilibrium position. So let's say this
is the wall and we have a spring and
here's the block of mass m.
The distance between where the spring is
located and the equilibrium position is
x. At the middle at the equilibrium
position x is zero. So the restoring
force will always be zero at the
equilibrium position.
K is known as the spring constant and K
has the units newtons per meter.
So let's say if you have a spring
constant of 100 newtons per meter, what
that means is that it requires 100
newtons of force to either stretch or
compress the spring by 1 meter from its
equilibrium position. So if you wish to
stretch it by 2 m, it requires 200
newtons of force.
So if you have a very stiff spring
that's hard to compress, the K constant
is very high. Let's say if K is a
th00and.
So for this spring, it requires 1,000
newtons of force just to stretch it by
one meter. So this spring is going to be
very stiff. It's hard to stretch or
compress.
This particular spring is going to be
easy to stretch or compress compared to
the other one. So, this spring is
relatively loose.
By the way, before we work on some
practice problems, I do want to mention
one thing. Any equation in Hook's law,
why is there a negative symbol for the
restoring force?
Why do we have this negative sign?
What's the reason for that?
So notice that if you apply a force
towards the right to stretch the spring,
the displacement vector will be towards
the right and the restoring force is
towards the left. Because the restoring
force is opposite to the displacement
vector,
F_sub_R is negative because it's always
opposite to the direction of motion.
The restoring force will always act in
such a way to bring the object back to
its equilibrium position. So if the
equil position is here, the restoring
force wants to bring it to the left.
Likewise,
Let's say if the spring is compressed,
the restoring force
wants to uh move it towards the right
back to its equilibrium position. And
remember at the equilibrium position,
the restoring force is zero since x is
equal to zero and f_sub_r is kx. So k *
0 is zero.
Let's work on some practice problems.
How much force is required to stretch a
300 Newton per meter spring by 25 cm?
So let's use the equation F is equal to
kx.
And let's not worry about the negative
sign.
If you see the unit newtons per meter,
that tells you that that value
represents the spring constant, which is
300 newtons per meter. And since it has
the unit meters in it, that tells us
that we need to convert centimeters into
meters.
It turns out that 100 cm
is equal to a single meter.
So to convert it we need to divide by
or move the decimal two units to the
left. So this is equal to 0.25 m which
is the value of x.
So what is 300 * 0.25
or what is 25% of 300?
This is going to be about 75.
So that is the force required to stretch
the spring by 25 cm.
How far can you compress the spring with
a force of 150 newtons?
Now let's think about this. It required
75 newtons to stretch the spring by 25
cm.
It also requires 75 newtons to compress
the spring by 25 cm.
So if we double the force to 150, the
amount that we can stress, I mean
stretch or compress the spring is going
to be twice the value. It's going to be
50 cm.
F= kx.
If you double the distance, if you
stretch it by two times the amount, the
force will increase by a factor of two.
Likewise, if you double the force, you
can double the distance that you stretch
or compress the spring bar.
Now, for those of you who prefer to use
an equation,
you can use this.
Let's divide f_sub_2 by f_sub_1.
f_sub_1 is equal to k * x1 and f_sub_2
is k * x2. Since we're dealing with the
same spring, K is the same.
So, as you can see, the force is
proportional to
x.
Let's say f_sub_1
is 75 newtons and we're looking for
f_sub_2.
X1. The distance that corresponds to 75
is 25 cmters.
Actually, we're not looking for F2. We
have F2. F2 is 150.
We're looking for X2.
150 / 75 is 2.
And at this point, we can cross
multiply.
So x2 is equal to 2 * 25 which is 50.
Here's another problem. It takes 200
newtons to stretch a spring by 40 cm.
How much force is required to stretch a
spring by 120 cm?
So 40 cm corresponds to a force of 200
newtons.
What is the force that's required to
triple the distance by a factor of
three?
If you triple the distance by a factor
of three, the force is going to increase
by a factor of 3. So the force that's
required is 600 newtons. Again, you can
use this equation. F_sub_2 over F_sub_1
is equal to X2 / X1. So we're looking
for F_sub_2 this time. f_sub_1 is 200
newtons.
X1 is 40 cm and X2 is 120 cmters. You
don't need to convert the units to
meters because the unit centimeters will
cancel.
So 120 / 40 is 3.
So therefore f_sub_2 / 200 is equal to
3. And if we multiply both sides by 200,
we can see that F_sub_2 is going to be 3
* 200, which is 600 newtons.
So that's how much force
is required to stretch a spring by 120
cm.
Now what about the second part to the
question? What is the value of the
spring constant?
So using the formula F is equal to Kx.
Solving for K, K is equal to the force /
the spring constant. So we can use the
force of 200 newtons. And instead of
using 40 cm, we need to convert it to
meters. So that's about 4 m.
/4
is equal to 500. So the spring constant
is 500 newtons per meter. So to stretch
the spring by a distance of 1 meter
requires a force of 500 newtons.
Now what about the last part of the
problem? How much work is required to
stretch a spring by 120 cm.
Work is equal to force times
displacement
which displacement could be represented
as X.
Now this is if you have a constant
force.
Now what about if the force is a
variable force? Example,
in this case,
work is equal to the integral of f * dx,
where f is a function of x.
And we know f is equal to k * x,
ignoring the negative sign. So work is
equal to the anti-derivative
of k * x dx.
To find the anti-derivative of kx, add
one to the exponent and divide by that
number.
The anti-derivative of x^ the 1st power
is x^2 / 2.
So the work required to stretch a spring
is going to be basically 12 kx^ 2. This
is also the potential energy that is
stored in a spring.
In some textbooks, you'll see this U
symbol. This is the elastic potential
energy of a spring. It's equal to 12
kx^2,
which is the work required to stretch it
or compress it.
So, k we know it's um 500 newtons per
meter.
I'm going to write it like this.
And x
is going to be 120 cm, but we'll need to
convert it to meters. So, let's divide
it by 100, which is 1.2 m squared.
And the unit meters will cancel,
which leaves behind newtons time meters.
There's 2 meters here. Since it's new
time me is equal to the unit jewels.
Half of 500 is 250 * 1.2^2
is equal to 360.
So it takes 360 jewels of work to
stretch this particular spring by 120
cm.
Now let's go back to our mass spring
system slash oscillator.
So let's say if we have a mass of m
attached to a spring and let's say
this is the
equilibrium position.
Now, as we mentioned before, the force
required to stretch the spring is the
apply force.
And whenever you stretch it, there's
going to be a restoring force that pulls
it back towards the left.
Now, you also need to know that at this
point, the net force is zero.
Now, this is only true while you're
holding it. As soon as you release the
mass from rest,
the applied force will disappear. At
that point, the net force is equal to
the restoring force.
And at this instant, as soon as you
release it, this object has maximum
acceleration.
And initially, the velocity is zero.
The velocity reaches its maximum value
once it reaches equilibrium. At
equilibrium, the restoring force is
zero. And because the restoring force is
zero, the acceleration is equal to zero
at the equilibrium position. However,
because the velocity is at a maximum,
it's moving towards the left.
So, because it has momentum, because
it's moving due to inertia, it's going
to continue to move to the left,
compressing the spring. As it begins to
compress the spring,
a restoring force is going to build up,
decelerating the object.
Once the object reaches a velocity of
zero, the restor is at its maximum
value, which means acceleration
it's at its maximum value at this point
as well. So make sure you understand
this that at the equilibrium position,
the velocity is at its maximum and the
acceleration is zero.
When it's fully stretched or compressed,
the acceleration
is at its maximum value and the velocity
is zero.
Now, if no friction is present in a
system, this oscillator will continue to
oscillate indefinitely.
If there's friction, friction is going
to oppose motion. So, in the first
picture, the object is moving towards
the left. So the force of friction will
be directed towards the right.
Now
in the middle it's still moving towards
the left. So friction is still directed
towards the right. And
on the last picture because the velocity
is zero, friction will be zero since
it's not moving instantaneously. But as
it begins to move towards the right,
friction will oppose it. So friction
always opposes motion.
By the way, once you release it, there's
no friction until it begins moving
towards the left. So, as it accelerates,
friction is going to oppose it.
Whenever there's friction present, the
oscillator will be dampened by it. The
amplitude will gradually decrease.
Now, let's talk about X and A.
at the equilibrium position. Let me draw
a new picture.
So let's say if we have an oscillator
and let's say this is the equilibrium
position
x is equal to zero at the equilibrium
and let's say at this point x is equal
to one.
So this is the maximum displacement.
The maximum displacement is represented
by the symbol capital A. So in this case
for this problem a is one.
At this position X is.5
since it's to the right of the
equilibrium position. And at this
position X is.5.
So let's say K is 100 newtons per meter.
What is the force the restoring force at
let's say a position of.5
include the appropriate sign as well. So
F is equal to kx it's going to be * 100
*.5
which is50.
So at this point
we have a force of -50. The negative
sign means that it's towards the left.
Now what about at this position? If we
plug in.5.
Okay, that does not look like a five.
It's going to be
*.5
which is pos 50.
Since the object is moving at this
location towards the left, the restoring
force is towards the right. And notice
that the force is positive 50 because
it's directed towards the right.
When the restoring force is directed
towards the left, notice that it's
negative.
Now, let's talk about the energy of this
particular oscillator.
When it's fully stretched and once you
release it, the acceleration is at its
maximum and the velocity is zero. The
kinetic energy of any moving object is
12 mv^ 2. So the kinetic energy is
dependent on the speed. So when it's
fully stretched or fully compressed,
let's say it's fully compressed at this
position here, the kinetic energy
is at a minimum because the velocity is
zero.
So K is going to equal zero when it's
fully stretched or compressed. Now at
the equilibrium position, the velocity
is at a max. So therefore K
is at its maximum value at the
equilibrium position.
As we mentioned before the acceleration
is zero at the equilibrium position and
the restoring force is equal to zero
since X is zero and F= KX. So K * Z is
zero.
Now what about the potential energy?
The potential energy
is at its maximum
when it's fully stretched or compressed.
But at equilibrium, the potential energy
is zero. The potential energy is equal
to 12 kx^ 2. Since x is zero at the
equilibrium position, the potential
energy is zero because 12 k * 0^ 2 is 0.
Now there's another thing that you need
to be familiar with and that is
mechanical energy.
The mechanical energy is the sum of the
kinetic energy and the potential energy.
Keep in mind
when the amplitude is one x can vary
anywhere between -1 to 1.
The mechanical energy depends on the
amplitude that is the maximum value of x
or the maximum displacement. So the
mechanical energy is 12 k a^ 2.
The kinetic energy is 12 mv ^2 and the
potential energy is 12 kx^2.
So whenever x is equal to a the
potential energy is the same as the
mechanical energy at this point the
kinetic energy is zero.
And whenever x is equal to zero that is
at the equilibrium position
potential energy is equal to zero. So
let me organize this information.
So let's say this is the equilibrium
position where x is zero.
At that point the potential energy will
be equal to zero.
So k is at its maximum. K equals the
mechanical energy.
The mechanical energy of the system is
constant if there's no friction.
The mechanical energy is the total
energy of the system.
Now, let's say if it's at the right, if
it's fully stretched
at this point, the maximum displacement
is equal to a.
So, when x is equal to a, the potential
energy is at a maximum. it's equal to
the mechanical energy which means that K
is equal to zero
and when it's fully compressed
P is still equal to the mechanical
energy and K is equal to zero.
Now sometimes you may need to calculate
the maximum acceleration and the maximum
velocity. What equations can we use to
do that? So let's start with maximum
velocity.
Now we said that
it's going to be the velocity is going
to be at its maximum when x is equal to
zero. So when x is equal to zero the
potential energy is zero. So this
disappears. So therefore 12 k a^2
is equal to 12 mv^2. We can multiply
both sides by two to get rid of the
fraction.
So k a^2 is equal to mv ^2.
To isolate v ^2 we need to divide both
sides by m.
So V
is equal to the square root of K / M
time the amplitude A.
So that's how you could find the maximum
velocity if you ever need to.
What about the acceleration? How can we
find a maximum acceleration? We know
that f is equal to kx.
And according to Newton's second law, F
is ma.
So what we need to do is divide both
sides by m. So k / m * x is equal to the
acceleration at any point. So that's the
acceleration as a function
of x.
Now the acceleration is at its maximum
value when x
is the maximum which is the amplitude.
So the maximum acceleration is k * a /
m.
Now what if we don't want to find the
maximum velocity? What if we need to
find the velocity as a function of x?
Let's say when x is 4.7. How can we do
that? Well, let's go back to our
conservation of energy equation.
Mechanical energy is equal to kinetic
plus potential energy.
So, let's begin by multiplying
everything by two.
2 * a half is 1. This will cancel all of
the fractions.
So we have k a^2 is equal to mv^2
+ kx^2.
Now let's subtract kx^ 2 by both sides.
k a^ 2us kx^2 is equal to m v^2. And now
let's factor out the gcf the greatest
common factor which is k. So this is
going to be a^2 - x^2.
Next, let's divide the expression by the
mass.
So, v ^ 2 is equal to k / m * a^ 2 -
x^2.
Now, what's our next step?
The next thing we need to do is take out
a
I mean a^2
if we take out a^2 a^2 / a^2 is simply 1
and this / a^2 that's going to be x^2 /
a^2.
So now what we want to do is take the
square root of both sides.
So the velocity as a function of x is
going to be the square roo of k / m
* a*
the square of 1 - x^ 2 / a^ 2. Now
the velocity can be positive or
negative. If the velocity is moving
towards the right it's positive. If it's
moving towards the left it's negative.
Now if you recall the quantity
km m * a is equal to the maximum
velocity.
So therefore we can rewrite the equation
like this. So the velocity as a function
of x is equal to plus or minus the
maximum velocity
times the square root
of 1 - x^2 / a^ 2. So make sure you uh
write this equation down. It might be
useful later.
Now there's something else that we need
to talk about and that is the frequency
and period of this spring mass
oscillator.
So let's say this is the equilibrium
position.
Now as the spring
moves to the left and as it moves back
to where it started from that is equal
to one cycle.
The distance of one cycle
is equal to basically four times the
value of x.
So from here back to its equilibrium
position, it travels a distance of x.
And then when it's fully compressed, it
travels another distance of x.
And then when it goes back to its
equilibrium position, that's another x
value. And when it returns to where it
started, that's X again. So the distance
of one cycle is four times its maximum
displacement. So we should really say
this is four * A since a represents the
maximum displacement.
So this is a.
Now what about the period and the
frequency?
The period is the time it takes to
complete one cycle.
The period which is represented by
capital T is the number of it's the time
divided by the number of cycles.
So let's say if it takes 30 seconds
to complete 10 cycles,
30 / 10 is three. That means that it
takes 3 seconds to complete a single
cycle. Therefore, the period is three.
So that's how you can find the period.
It's the total time divided by the total
number of cycles or the time it takes to
complete one single cycle. The frequency
is the number of cycles per second. So
if you take the total number of cycles
and divide it by the total time, you can
get the frequency.
So, for example, let's say if it takes,
let me choose a nice number. Um,
let's say if this system can cycle 200
times in 10 seconds. So, if it makes 200
cycles
in 10 seconds,
that means that it's doing 20 cycles
in 1 second. So, the frequency is 20 or
20 hertz. Hertz is the unit of
frequency. Now frequency and period are
inversely related. The frequency is 1 /
the period and the period is 1 / the
frequency.
So let's work on some problems. What
happens to the following if the maximum
displacement of the spring is doubled?
So what happens to the total energy of
the system? The total energy of the
system is the mechanical energy. Now the
first thing we want to do is write an
equation that relates the mechanical
energy with the maximum displacement and
that's this equation. Me is equal to 12
k a^ 2 where a is the maximum
displacement.
So if we double the value of a what
happens to me for these types of
problems anything that's constant or
remains the same replace it with a one.
So 12 k we're just going to replace it
with one and plug in the value of a. If
you double the value of a because the
function is squared, the mechanical
energy will increase by a factor of
four. If we were to triple the value of
a, the mechanical energy will increase
by 3^ 2, which is 9. If we quadruple the
value of a, the mechanical energy will
increase by a factor of 16.
Now, what about part B? The maximum
velocity. What equation can we write
that relates maximum velocity to the
maximum displacement? Now we came up
with the equation earlier. We said that
the maximum velocity
is equal to
the square root of k / m where k is the
spring constant times the maximum
displacement.
So notice that it's raised to the first
power. So if we double the value of a
and this is going to stay the same. So
we're going to replace it with one. The
velocity will increase by a factor of
two. If you triple the displacement, the
three. If you cut the displacement in
half, the velocity will decrease by a
factor of two or it's going to be 1/2 of
its original value. Now what about part
C? The maximum acceleration. The
equation that we wrote for that is this
equation. The maximum acceleration is
equal to K / M times the maximum
displacement. So if you double the value
of the maximum displacement, the
acceleration will increase by a factor
of two. If you triple it, the
acceleration will triple. If you reduce
it by 1/2, the acceleration will reduce
by a factor of two.
Let's work on this problem. A massless
spring is pulled by 30 cm from its
natural length and then released. The
spring is attached to a4 kg block and
oscillates across a horizontal friction
with surface.
Let's begin by calculating the maximum
velocity.
So if you want to you can draw a
picture.
So here's the block and it rests across
a horizontal surface and let's say this
is the equilibrium position.
So right now it's pulled by 30 cm which
is.3 m.
So let's make a list of what we know. A
the maximum displacement is.3
and K the spring constant is 300 newtons
per meter.
What equation do we need to calculate
the maximum velocity?
The maximum velocity is simply
the square root of K / M * A. The mass
is4 kg. So we have everything we need to
find the maximum velocity.
So this is going to be 300 /4
*.3
300 /4
is 750.
The square root of 750 is 27.386
*.3
and you should get a maximum velocity of
8.216 216
m/s.
So now what about part B? What's the
maximum acceleration?
So let's use this equation. It's equal
to K * A / M. So it's going to be 300
*.3
/ 04.3
/4 is basically 75 * 300 that's 225. So
the maximum acceleration is 225 m/s
squared.
Now what about part C?
How can we find the velocity at a
position of 20 cm from its natural
length?
So, keep in mind the maximum velocity
was about 8.2 something
8.216.
We can use this equation.
The velocity as a function of x is equal
to the maximum velocity times the square
root
1 - x^ 2 / a^ 2.
That's the equation that we had earlier
uh in this video. So we want to find the
velocity at a position of 20 cm from its
natural length.
Now, because we have a ratio between x
and a, it doesn't really matter if you
use centimeters or meters. The units
simply have to match because they're
both going to cancel. Centimeters over
centimeters and meters over meters will
cancel. So, we can plug in 20 cm if we
want to.
So, the maximum velocity is 8.216.
And then this is going to be 1 - 20^ 2 /
30^ 2
/ 30^ 2 is about 4 over 9 which is4
repeating and 1 minus that number is
about.5 repeating and the square root of
that is 7454*
8.216.
So, you should get a velocity of about
let's make some space.
6.124.
So, your answer should be less than the
maximum velocity. If for some reason
it's larger, you know it's not correct.
Now, what about the next part? How can
we find the restoring force 20 cm from
its natural length?
Now let's say 20 cm is located at this
point. We know the restoring force is
directed towards the left which means
that it should be negative.
So the restoring force is equal to * kx.
So this is going to be negative
300 newtons per meter
time x which is 2 m. Now in this case we
need to convert centimeters to meters
because we're using k and k is in
meters.
3 * 2 is 6. So 300 *2 must be 60.
So the restoring force is 60 newtons.
It's negative because it's directed
towards the left.
Now, what about the acceleration?
Well, we know that the force is equal to
mass time acceleration. So, the
acceleration is the restoring force / m.
And the restor is -60 newton. The mass
is4 kg.
So -60 /4
is -150 m/s squared. Keep in mind the
maximum acceleration was 225 and this is
less than 225. So that works out.
Now you can also use this equation.
Acceleration is equal to
K / M * X.
It's similar to this equation. The
maximum acceleration is K * A / M. But
here it's K * X / M. So K is 300, X is20
and M is4.
So if you use this equation, you should
get the same answer
which is 150. Now we know it should be
because the resultant I mean the
restoring force is towards the left
acceleration
and the force that causes that
acceleration are usually in the same
direction. So because the restoring
force is negative the acceleration is
negative which really means that this
equation should have a negative sign. So
let's go ahead and add it.
So that is it for this problem.
In this problem, we have a vertical
spring.
So let's say this is the spring
without a mass attached to it. Now once
we add a mass to it, it's going to
stretch.
Now it stretches by
4 m.
So this is the new equilibrium position
of the mass.
Now if we stretch it even further
by an additional
20 m from its new uh equilibrium
position.
Once we release it, it's going to bounce
up and down.
So with this information
determine the spring constant, the
amplitude and everything else. So let's
focus on the spring constant.
We can use this picture to find the
value of the spring constant.
The applied force that stretches the
spring from its original position is
basically the weight force of the object
which is mg.
The spring wants to go back to its
original length.
So the restor
is equal to the weight force so that the
net force is zero creating that new
equilibrium position.
So f_sub_r is equal to mg
and the restoring force is kx
and g is 9.8. So you really don't need
to worry about the negative sign. They
will cancel. Now let's solve for k. So k
is going to be equal to mg / x. So the
mass is 2 kg. G is 9.8. 8 and it
stretches by a distance of4 m.
So 2 * 9.8 is 19.6 /4
is 49.
So K is 49
newtons per meter.
Now what about part B? What is the
amplitude in this problem?
What do you think the amplitude is equal
to?
Now remember this is the new equilibrium
position and it's stretched 20 m from
that equilibrium position. So therefore
the amplitude is 20.
So once we release it from this position
it's going to bounce up and down 20 from
this position. So it's going to go up 20
and down 20 m.
Now what about C? How can we calculate
the maximum acceleration?
What is the equation that we need? If
you recall the maximum acceleration
is equal to the spring constant time the
amplitude divided by the mass. So it's
49 *2
/ the mass of 2.
So the maximum acceleration is 4.9 m/s
squared.
Now what about d the maximum velocity?
The equation that we need for that
is the square root of k / m * a
49 / 2 is 24.5 and the square root of
that
is about 4.95*
*2
that's about.99
m/s.
So now what about part E? What is the
kinetic energy, potential energy and the
mechanical energy when it's 10 m from
its equilibrium position?
So let's find the
potential energy first.
The potential energy is 12 kx^2
which is basically 12 * 49 times an x
value of10
49 *10^ 2 that's about49
* half that's 0.25.
So the potential energy
is.245
Jew.
Now what about the kinetic energy?
The kinetic energy is equal to 12
mv^2.
Now we can't use the maximum velocity.
The velocity will be.99. It will be at
its max when x is zero at the
equilibrium position. But we're not at
the equilibrium position. X is 10. So we
got to find the velocity first at 10.
The velocity as a function of X is the
maximum velocity*
of 1 - X^ 2 / A^ 2.
So the maximum velocity is about.99
and x is 0.1 a the amplitude is 2.1^
2 /2^ 2 is 1/4 1 - 1/4 is 3/4s and the
square of 3/4s is about 866
times.99
you should get 8574
m/s. second.
Now that we have the velocity,
we can now use this equation to find the
kinetic energy. So let's plug it into
that equation. So K is equal to 12 * the
mass which is 2 kg
time the speed.8574
2. So half of 2 is 1 and 1 *85
74^ 2 is about 735 jew. So that's the
kinetic energy
735.
Now let's calculate the mechanical
energy.
We're going to do it two ways.
So first let's use the equation
mechanical energy is equal to 12 K * the
amplitude squared.
So K is 49 and the amplitude
is 20 m or2 m2
is 1 over 25 or 04*
49 which is 1.96. Half of that is.98.
So the mechanical energy which
represents the total energy of the
system is.98 Jew. Another way in which
we could find it is by adding the
potential energy and the kinetic energy.
So if we add245 plus 735 it also gives
us the same answer of 98 uh jewels.
So
let's say if you didn't know the
equation to find the velocity at any
point x, you can use this to get the
mechanical energy. And if you subtract
the mechanical energy by the potential,
that's one way you can get the kinetic
energy.
So there's different ways of solving
different things that you may need. So
you're not faced with one option.
There's many options that you can use.
Try this problem. A spring is
compressed.35
m with a 0.25 kg block by an applied
force of 500 newtons.
What speed will the block have as soon
as it's released from the spring across
a horizontal frictionless surface?
So let's say this is the wall
and
we have a compressed spring
and the mass attached to it
and let's say this is the horizontal
frictionless surface.
Now it's compressed by an applied force
of 500 ntons
and it's compressed by a distance let's
say of.35
m
and the mass of the block is 0.25.
Right now the applied force is balanced
by a restoring force of 500 Ntons. So as
soon as we release it the applied force
will disappear and it's going to
accelerate towards the right
due to this restoring force of 500.
Now this restoring force is not
constant.
As the spring expands, the restoring
force will decrease eventually to zero.
At that point, the mass will be released
from the spring and it's going to move
to the right at constant speed. So, when
it's completely released from the
spring, when it's no longer attached to
the spring, what is the speed that the
block will have?
How can we calculate that value?
Take a minute and work on that example.
The first thing that we need to do is
find the spring constant K.
So F is equal to Kx. Therefore K is the
force / X. So we have an applied force
of 500 newtons which compresses the
spring by.35 m.
So if we divide these two,
we'll see that the spring constant
is about
rounded to the nearest whole number
newtons per meter. So now that we have
the spring constant, we can use
conservation of energy to calculate
how fast it's going to move.
So the mechanical energy
is equal to the kinetic energy
or you can say the potential energy
stored in the spring is equal to the
kinetic.
The mechanical energy is 12 k a^2. If
you use the potential energy equation,
it's 12 kx^2. But in this case, x is
equal to a because it's stretched. I
mean, it's compressed all the way. X is
basically at its maximum displacement
when it's.35.
So we'll use the symbol a though. 12 k a
2 is equal to 12 mv^ 2.
So if we multiply both sides by two, we
can get rid of the 12.
So K is 1429,
A is.35,
M is.25,
and we need to solve for V.35^
2*
1429.
That's about 175. And if we divide that
by 0.25,
we can see that V ^2 is equal to about
700.21.
And now if we take the square root of
both sides,
the velocity is about 26.5
m/s.
So that's how fast it's going to be
moving.
By the way, let's say if we wanted to
find the kinetic energy
of the object
as soon as it's released
using this equation, it's 12 times the
mass, which is 0.25
times the speed, which is really 26.46
squared.
The kinetic energy of the object is
about 87.53
Jew.
Now another equation that you can use to
get that answer is the work equation. So
keep in mind as soon as we release it,
there's a restoring force that's going
to accelerate towards the right.
Work is equal to force times distance.
However, we don't have a constant force.
We have a variable force.
Now, let's assume that this force
decreases constantly. Well, it actually
does. So, we don't really have to
assume.
The force will decrease at a constant
rate from its maximum value of 500 to
zero.
as the block is displaced by.35 m.
So basically
the energy transferred by this force
should be equal to the kinetic energy
which is 87.5.
So how can we find the area of that
triangle?
Well area is basically 12 base time
height or 12 *
the height which is 500. That's
basically the restoring force times the
base which is the displacement of.35.
Half of 500 is 250 and 250 *.35
gives you 87.5 Jew.
So that's another way in which you can
calculate the kinetic energy gained by
the block is by using the work equation.
But if you're going to use the restoring
force, you need to add a 1/2 to it
because the restoring force is not
constant.
Now there are some other topics that you
need to know and that is the equations
for the period and the frequency as it
is related to the mass and the spring
constant of a spring.
Now we need to compare circular motion
with the simple harmonic motion of a
spring.
So let's draw a circle.
Now
let's say
if an object on a circle
moves from let's say point A to point B
as it moves this way. If you can view
the circle
horizontally from this perspective
rather than viewing it from uh top to
bottom. If you can just have like a side
view,
all you will see is that this particle
is moving in the negative x direction.
You're only going to see the
displacement along the x-axis.
Now, as it moves from, let's say,
position B to position C,
if you take a side view of it, you're
going to see it's still moving towards
the left.
Now, as it moves from
C to D, it's going to appear as if it
it's moving towards the right, which it
is.
And from D to A,
it's moving this way. So if you can view
it from the side, circular motion would
seem similar to the oscillation of a
spring as it moves back and forth.
So knowing that
we can say that the
speed of the object around a circle is
basically the distance that it travels
divided by the time. And the distance
around a circle is the circumference
which is 2 pi r.
The time it takes to make one revolution
or one cycle is the period which is
represented by capital t.
Now notice that the radius of the circle
is basically the amplitude.
So we can replace r with a.
Now we no longer need this picture.
So now at this point let's multiply both
sides by t. So vt is equal to 2 pi a.
And now let's divide both sides by v.
So the period is 2 pi * the amplitude /
the velocity.
And if you recall the maximum velocity
we said was equal to
the square roo of k / m * a.
So to solve for a, we can multiply both
sides by the square root of m / k. So
that m will cancel on the right and k
will cancel on the right as well. So v *
the of m / k is equal to a. So now
let's replace this a with this
expression.
So the period t is 2i / v times v
max time m / k.
So we can cancel v.
So therefore the period
of a spring is 2i * the square
of m / k. So now let's talk about this
equation.
If we increase the mass of the spring,
what's going to happen to the period?
Will the time it takes to complete one
cycle, will it increase or decrease?
Because the mass is in the numerator of
the fraction, the period will increase
as well.
So let's say if you double the mass of
the spring, what effect will it have on
the period? So for these questions,
plug in the value that is being changed.
Everything else, plug in the one. So if
we double the mass,
the period will increase by the roo
of two. Now what if we quadruple the
mass?
The period will increase by the square
roo of 4 which is two. So if you
quadruple the mass, the period will
double.
If you increase the mass by a factor of
9,
the period will triple in value.
What if you reduce the mass by 1/2?
the square root of 12 which is 1 over
2 that's 2 over2.
So the period will increase well
actually it's going to decrease by
2 over2 that's about 707. So it's
going to be 70% of its value
or you could say it's reduced by a
factor of 2 because you're dividing
it by 2.
So if you decrease the mass to half of
its value, the period is going to be
reduced by a factor of 2.
It's going to be 70% of its original
value or 70.7.
Now what about the spring constant?
Let's say if we increase the value of K,
what happens to the period?
The period will decrease since K is on
the bottom.
So if you double the value of K,
the period will decrease
by the square root of two. It's going to
be 70% or 70.7% of its original value.
If you quadruple the value of K,
the period is going to be 1/2 of its
original value.
Now what if you reduce the spring
constant by 1/4?
What effect will that have on the
period? 1 / 1/4 is 4. So if you decrease
K to 1/4 its value, the period will
double.
Now let's think about what this means.
So we could see from the equation why
the period will increase if we increase
the mass. But
let's understand it conceptually.
As you increase the mass of the block,
it's going to have more inertia. So it's
going to be harder to move. As a result,
it's going to have less acceleration. F
is equal to ma.
If the force is constant, whenever you
increase the mass, the acceleration will
decrease.
So if it has a lower acceleration, it's
going to move more slowly. And
therefore, an object that moves slowly
takes a longer time to get to its
destination. Therefore, as you increase
the mass, the period increases. Since
the object is heavier, it's going to
take a longer time to to move back and
forth. And so that's why the period
increases.
Now what about the second situation
where if we increase the value of K the
period decreases.
A large K value means that the spring
requires a greater force to compress or
stretch it. So the spring is stiff.
Because the spring is stiff,
it doesn't really move very far.
It doesn't really it's not easily
stretched or compressed. So it can
vibrate faster
as a result because it can vibrate
faster
its period will be reduced.
So keep in mind K is FX.
So a large K constant means that a
greater force is required to stretch it
with the same distance. And if the force
is greater, the acceleration
will be greater as well. And a higher
acceleration means a fast moving object.
It can quickly gain speed. And if the
object is moving faster, then it's going
to take a longer time, I mean a shorter
time actually, to oscillate back and
forth. And so that's why as you increase
the value of K, it oscillates faster and
the period is reduced.
Now going back to this equation,
there's one more equation that you need
and that is frequency. Frequency is 1 /
period. So the frequency is going to be
1 / 2i * k / m. So this time
if you increase the K value,
if you increase the spring constant,
a greater force is required to stretch
or compress the spring, which means that
there's going to be a greater
acceleration, which means that it's
oscillating faster. And because it's
oscillating faster, the frequency will
increase.
Now if you increase the mass,
the object requires
a greater acceleration to move it back
and forth. But if the force is constant,
as you increase the mass, the
acceleration will be reduced. And so
it's going to be moving slower, so to
speak. So therefore, the frequency will
be reduced.
Frequency and speed, they're related. An
object that can oscillate back and forth
at a faster rate will have a higher
frequency.
And an object that oscillates at a
slower rate will have a low frequency.
So as you increase the value of K, the
speed of the oscillations will increase
and so the frequency will increase. If
you increase the mass, heavy objects
tend to move slower and so the frequency
will decrease.
A spring attached to a.25 kg block is
stretched horizontally across a
frictionless floor. 25 m by an applied
force of 200 newtons.
Calculate the frequency and period of
the oscillations of this mass spring
system. So let's begin by drawing a
picture.
So here we have a spring
attached to a mass
and here is the floor.
So as we stretch it with an applied
force
once we release it the spring will
oscillate back and forth.
So how can we find the frequency of the
oscillations? Well we can use this
equation 1 / 2i * the square root
of k / m.
Now in this problem we don't have the
spring constant K. So we need to find
it. But we do have the applied force and
the distance that it's stretched by. So
K is equal to the force / X. So that's
200 newtons /.25
m. So let's go ahead and divide those
two numbers.
So K is 800 newtons per meter.
Now that we have the spring constant, we
can calculate the frequency. So it's 1 /
2 pi * the of k which is 800
/ the mass which is 0.25 kg.
800 / 0.25 is 3200. And the square root
of 3200 is about 56.57.
And let's divide that by 2 pi.
and you should get a frequency of 9
hertz.
Now that we have the frequency, we can
easily calculate the period. The period
is simply 1 / f, which is basically 1 /
9.
1 / 9 is about 0.1 repeating. So the
period is about1
seconds. So it takes1
seconds to make a full cycle. That is it
takes 111 seconds for the block to
travel towards the left and back to its
original position.
And in 1 second
the spring will oscillate nine times.
That's the frequency, the number of
cycles that occurs in 1 second. So in 1
second it's going to go backwards and
forwards nine times in that single
second.
Here's another problem you can try. When
a 70 kg person gets on a 1200 kg car,
the springs compress by 2 cm,
what will be the frequency of vibration
when the car hits a bump?
So, first let's find K. So, F is equal
to Kx.
The force that compresses the spring by
2 centimeters is the weight of the
person because once he gets on the car,
X changes by 2 cm. So we only need to
use the weight of that person and not
the weight of the car and a person to
find K.
So K is equal to mg / X. So it's the
mass of the person times 9.8 8 /
2 cm converted to meters. To convert
centimeters to meters, divide by 100. So
this is 02 m.
So it's 70 * 9.8 / that number.
And the spring constant is 34,300
newtons per meter. Now that we have the
spring constant, we can calculate the
frequency of vibration.
Now when the car hits a bump,
you have to consider the mass of the
person and the car because the spring is
attached to both or it's affected by the
mass of the person and the car. It has
to support the weight of both.
So using the equation f is equal to 1 /
2 pi * the of k / m. This is 1 over
2 pi
time 34,300
divided by the total mass. That's uh 70
+ 1 1200 or 1270.
34,300
/ 1270
is about 27.
And the square root of 27 is about 5.2.
And if you divide that by 2 pi,
you should get a frequency of83
hertz.
So that's it for this particular
problem.
So here's another problem. Here we have
an insect caught in a spiderweb. We have
the mass of the insect and the frequency
and we need to find the spring constant
K.
So let's start with the equation f is
equal to 1 / 2i
* of
k / m.
Now let's solve for k.
So first let's multiply both sides by 2
pi.
So 2 pi f is equal to the square root of
k / m.
Now at this point we're going to square
both sides so we can get rid of the
square root on the right. So 2 p^2
is equal to k / m. Now the last thing we
need to do is multiply both sides by m.
So now we have the equation that we
need.
So the spring constant K is equal to the
mass * 2 pi F squar
and let's assume that
the mass of the spiderweb is negligible.
So we're only concerned with the mass of
the insect.
Now we need to plug in the mass in
kilograms. To convert grams to kilograms
you can divide by a th00and or instead
of writing 0.25g you can write 0.25. 25
* 10 - 3 kg.
1 g is about 0.1 kg or 1 * 10 - 3 kg.
And the frequency is 20 hertz.
2 pi * 20 is about 40 pi or 125.66.
If you square it, you should get 15791.
And then if you multiply by 0.25 * 10us
3,
this should give you a spring constant
of 3.95
newtons per meter.
Now that we have the spring constant K,
how can we answer the second part of the
problem?
So if the mass
is now 10 g, what is the frequency? So
using the equation 1 / 2i * k
m,
it's going to be different.
So k is about 3
9478.
3.95 is the right answer. And the mass
is going to be.1 * 10us 3 kg.
So 3.9478
/.1 * 10us 3 that's 39,478.
If you take the square root of that you
should get 198.69
and then divide that by 2 pi
and this will be equal to 31.6
hertz.
Now you can get the same answer even if
you don't have the value of k. And let
me show you.
So let's say if we had a ratio f_sub_2 /
f_sub_1.
f_sub_2 is 1 / 2i square k /
m2.
And we're assuming that k is the same
since we're dealing with the same spider
web. And this is going to be the same
thing but m1. So we can cancel the 2 pi
and we can cancel k.
So we get the equation f_sub_2 / f_sub_1
is equal to the of 1 / m2 /
the of 1 / m1.
So how can we simplify
the expression that we have on the
right? What would you do to simplify it?
Let's multiply the top and the bottom by
the square root of m1. If we do that,
m1 will cancel on the bottom.
And so we're going to have f_sub_2 /
f_sub_1.
And if you multiply 1 over m2 * m1, this
is just going to be the square root of
m1 over m2.
So this is the equation that we can use
to get the answer to the second part of
the problem if we don't have the spring
constant k.
So notice that a frequency of 20 hertz
corresponds to a mass of 25 g.
Because we have a ratio of the masses,
we don't need to convert it to kilogram.
So m1 is going to be 0.25 g.
Now we're looking for the frequency
f_sub_2 when the mass is10.25
/10
is 2.5. And the square root of 2.5 is
about 1.581.
So f_sub_2 / 20 is equal to 1.581.
To solve for f_sub_2, multiply both
sides by 20. So 1.581 * 20
is 31.62 hertz,
which is about the answer that we got a
few minutes ago.
A block of mass attached to a spring
with a constant of 200 newtons per meter
vibrates at 15 hertz. What is the
frequency of vibration if the same block
is attached to a spring of 500 newtons
per meter? So the mass is constant here.
The only thing that changes is the
spring constant and f.
So we know that f is equal to 1 /
2i *
of
k / m. So we can write a ratio f2 /
f_sub_1 is 1 / 2 pi square k2 m. So
we we're going to write the subscript
for k since k changes. But m is
constant. So we don't need to write the
subscript for m. So we can cancel the 2
pi and the mass. So we're going to get
this equation f_sub_2 / f_sub_1 is equal
to the square t of k2 / k1.
So as you increase the spring constant
the force will increase.
So I mean not the force but the
frequency will increase. So the
frequency should be higher than 15 htz.
So f_sub_1 is 15 and that corresponds to
a k constant of 200. K2 is 500 and we're
looking for f_sub_2. So if we divide 500
by 200, that's 2.5. And the square root
of 2.5 is 1.581.
So f_sub_2 / 15 is that number. So to
find f2, we need to multiply 1.581 by 15
and you should get a frequency of 23.7
hertz.
A block under goes SHM with amplitude
point4. That's simple harmonic motion.
If you see sho that's a simple harmonic
oscillator.
What is the total distance that it
travels in eight periods?
Now keep this in mind
the distance that it travels in one
period or one cycle is four times the
amplitude. Let's say this is the
equilibrium position.
This is the amplitude, the amount that
it's fully stretched by.
So
for to for this block to travel one
complete cycle, it has to travel a
towards the equilibrium position and
another distance of A and then back
back towards where it started. So as you
can see the distance that it travels in
one cycle or one period is 4 * a.
So 4 *4
is 1.6 m. So in one period it's going to
travel a distance of 1.6 m.
In 8 periods it's going to be 1.6 * 8
which is about 12.8 m.
So that's the total distance that the
block will travel in a periods.
Now there's some other functions
that can describe the motion of a mass
spring system.
So let's say if we have a vertical
spring
and currently it's compressed and let's
say this is the equilibrium position.
So it's capable of bouncing up and down.
So therefore this is going to be equal
to the amplitude
and this will be a
Now as it bounced up and down, if you
plot this
on a graph, let's say time is the x-
axis
and the displacement is on the y- axis.
So this is going to be the maximum
displacement and here's negative a.
So according to this graph, it's
starting at its compressed position. So
that's at the top. If you graph it over
time, it's going to form a sinosoidal
function.
It's basically a sine wave. Now, because
it started at the top, this is the
cosine function. If it started at the
middle, it would be s.
Now if we draw the circle that we had
earlier in this video,
this is x and the radius of the circle
is a
on the inside. This is the angle theta
and this is the right triangle.
According to uh circa, if you've taken
trigonometry at this point, you know
that coine
of the angle theta is equal to the
adjacent side / the hypotenuse.
That's the cup part in SOA.
The adjacent side is the side that's
very close to the angle. So that's X.
The hypotenuse is across the box. That's
a. So cosine theta is X / A. So if you
multiply both sides by A, you can get
the value of X.
So therefore x is equal to a cossine
theta.
Now we know that linear displacement is
equal to velocity multiplied by time d=
vt.
Angular displacement is equal to omega
which is angular velocity multiplied by
time.
Now perhaps you have seen this equation
as you've studied rotational kinematics.
If you haven't, you can look up my video
that I've created on YouTube. You can
check that out and you'll see that
equation.
Omega, which is the angular velocity,
it's equal to 2i * the frequency.
So therefore, we could say x is equal to
a cosine
omega * t since theta
equals omega * t. And then we can
replace omega with 2 pi f. So x the
position function with respect to time
is equal to the amplitude time cosine
2 pi f * t. So make sure that you write
this equation down.
This is an equation that you need to
know.
Now if you taken calculus you know that
the derivative of the position function
x gives you the instantaneous velocity.
So let's find the derivative.
The derivative of cosine is equal to
negative sign.
Now you have to keep the angle the same
the 2 pi ft and then you have to
differentiate the nested function or the
inside part of s which is 2 pi ft. The
derivative of 2 pi ft is simply 2 pi f.
t is the variable that you're
differentiating with respect to. The
derivative of 5x is 5. The derivative of
9x is 9. The derivative of 8t is 8. So
the derivative of 2 pi ft is 2 pi f.
By the way, for those of you who haven't
taken calculus and who want to
understand how to find the derivative of
a function to understand this step, you
can find my video on derivatives in
YouTube. You just got to search for it.
You may have to type in like power rule,
product rule, quotient rule, but you
only need the power rule for this
function. And also, you need to know how
to find the derivative of trigonometric
functions as well, which you can also
find out on YouTube. So, now let's
continue.
So we need to replace a few things at
this point.
Let's replace f. We know that the
frequency
is 1 / 2i
time the of k / m.
In addition, earlier in this video, we
mentioned that the amplitude is equal to
the maximum velocity
times the square roo of m / k. And
this came from the equation vax is equal
to km
* a. So let's replace a with this
expression and let's replace f with that
expression.
So the velocity as a function of time is
going to be a which is vax
time of m / k*
sin 2 f_t
* 2i
* f which is 1 / 2 pi square k / m.
So we can cancel 2 pi, we can cancel k
and we can cancel m. So now we have the
velocity function
with respect to time.
So here it is
the instantaneous velocity is equal to
the maximum velocity.
Let's put the negative in front. So
negative vax time sin
2 pi ft and that's it. So make sure that
you add this to the list of equations
that you need to know.
Now instead of writing vmax some
textbooks
will use the symbol vo but it's the same
thing. It's the maximum velocity.
Now let's find the acceleration.
The acceleration is the derivative of
the velocity function.
So vmax is a constant. We don't have to
change that. The derivative of s is
cosine.
And the derivative of 2 pi ft is 2 pi f.
Now let's replace vmax with what we
wrote before. We set equal to
k / m * a.
And the frequency
as we mentioned before is 1 / 2i
square
k / m.
So we can cancel 2 pi.
k * k is k^ 2 and m * m is m^2. This
time they don't cancel. So we have k^2
m^2
a cosine
2 pi ft.
The square root of k^2 is simply k and
the square root of m^ 2 is simply m.
So the acceleration as a function of
time is k / m * a cosine 2 pi ft.
Now if you recall F is equal to Kx and
the force is basically mass time
acceleration and let's replace X with
the amplitude A. So the maximum
acceleration is K * the amplitude / M
which is exactly what we have here. So
therefore we could say that the
acceleration function with respect to
time is equal to the maximum
acceleration. You can say a kn or simply
just a max time cosine 2 pi f_t.
So t is the variable, f is a constant
and the maximum acceleration is a
constant. So here's the third equation
that you need.
A 75 kg mass vibrates according to the
equation x= 6 cosine 9.2t. 2 t x is in
meters, t is in seconds. So what is the
amplitude?
Now we have the position function with
respect to time and we know the equation
is a * cosine 2 pi ft.
So the amplitude is simply the number in
front of cosine. Therefore the amplitude
is 6. That's the maximum displacement of
the 75 kg mass. Now, what about part B,
the frequency?
Notice that the 9.2, the number in front
of T, is equal to 2 pi F. So, let's set
2 pi F equal to 9.2 and let's solve for
F. To solve for F, divide both sides by
2 pi. So, F is 9.2
/ 2 pi.
So, the frequency is about 1.464 464
hertz.
Now that we have the frequency, we could
find the period which is 1 / the
frequency or 1 / 1.464
which is about
3 seconds.
Now how can we find the spring constant?
What equation would you use to find it?
You can use this equation. The spring
constant is the mass time 2 pi f^ squ.
We've established this equation earlier
in the video.
So k is going to be the mass which is
75*
2 * the frequency 1.464
squared.
2 pi * 1.464
is 9.198. And if you square that, you
should get about 84.61
* 75.
So K is equal to 63.46
newtons per meter.
So now the next thing we need to do is
find the total energy which is really
the mechanical energy of the system and
that's 12 * K * the amplitude squar.
So 12 * 63.46
* 6^ 2.
Half of 63.46 46 is about 31.73
and if you multiply that by6^ squ you
should get 11.42 Jew.
So that is the total energy of the
system.
Now what is the potential and the
kinetic energy at 0.2 2 and 6.
So let's say if this is the spring and
let's say this is its compressed
position. Let's say this is the
equilibrium position.
At equilibrium, we know that X is zero.
When it's fully stretched or compressed,
X is equal to A.
which is about 6.
When x is zero, we know that the
velocity is at its maximum, which means
kinetic energy it's at its maximum. So
at x equals z, the kinetic energy is
equal to the total energy, which is
11.42.
And when x is zero, the potential energy
is therefore equal to zero. So that's
the answer for the first part. So when x
is zero, k equals me, that's 11.42
jewels and p is equal to zero.
Now what about the other extreme? When x
is 6,
when it's fully compressed or stretched,
the kinetic energy will be zero at this
point. But the potential energy will not
be zero. It's going to be 11.42
at a displacement of 6.
So whenever it's fully stretched or
compressed, it's not moving. The
velocity is zero and all of the energy
is stored in the form of potential
energy. But at the equilibrium position,
it's moving at its greatest speed.
There's no restoring force at that
point. So all of the energy is in the
form of kinetic energy and there's no
potential energy. Now what about in the
middle somewhere between 0 2 I mean
somewhere between 0 and 6 which is at 0
2 in the middle it's going to have
kinetic and potential energy. So we need
to use the equations um to get that
answer.
Now there's two ways you can do this.
You can do it the fast way or the long
way but it's good to understand both so
you can fully uh get the sense of this
chapter. So let's do it the fast way
first. Let's find the potential energy
when it's 2 m from the equilibrium
position. So we can use the equation 12
kx^2.
So that's 12 times the value of k which
I forgot what that is since I uh erased
the board. But let me recalculate it.
So K was uh 63.46.
So let me just write that here just in
case I need that again. And X is 2.
So therefore the potential energy
at this point is about 1.27 Jew.
Now if you know the mechanical energy
and the potential energy you can find
the kinetic.
The kinetic energy is simply the
difference between a mechanical energy
and a potential energy. So 11.42us
1.27
is about 10.15.
So that is the kinetic energy. That's
how you can find it the fast way.
Now let's use the long way to get the
kinetic energy.
So before we can find the kinetic
energy, we need to use this equation. We
got to find the velocity at 2.
So it's vax * the of 1 - x^2 / a^
2.
Now we got to find vmax first. So vax is
equal to the of k / m * a. So
that's going to be the square of
63.46 46 / the mass which is 75
times the amplitude which is 6
63.46 / 75 that's like 84.61.
If you take the square root of that you
should get 9.2
* 6. So the maximum velocity
is 5.519.
So now we could find a velocity at 2. So
that's going to be 5.519
square 1 minus let's plug in the x
value of 2. So2^ 2 / 6^ 22
/6^ 2 is basically 1 over 9 which is 0.1
repeating 1 minus that is8 repeating.
take the square root and then that's
9428 multiplied by 5.519.
So V
at this position is about 5.203.
It's slightly less than the maximum
velocity. So now we can find the kinetic
energy. It's 12 mv^ 2. So 12 times the
mass
time the velocity squared
5.203
2 is about 27.07
* 75 *.5
and you should get 10.15 Jew.
So you get the same answer. But as you
can see taking the difference between a
mechanical energy and a potential energy
was a lot easier. to make sure you know
how to find the kinetic energy using
both techniques.
A 0.55 kg block vibrates according to
the equation x is equal to 1.5 cosine
12.4t.
Determine the equations of the velocity
and acceleration as a function of time.
So let's write the generic equations. So
we know the position function is a
cosine
2 pi ft.
Now by the way you can describe the
position function in terms of sign as
well. It all depends on where the block
starts at t equals z. For this function
if you use in positive cosine the block
has to start from the top if it's a
vertical spring. If it's horizontal, it
has to start towards the right of the
equilibrium position.
If it's starting at the equilibrium
position, you need to use the sign
function.
Now the velocity function
we said
it was negative vo which is vmax
time sine
2 pi f_t.
So notice for the velocity function we
don't need to change the inside part of
the s and cosine function. So 2 pi ft is
12.4t. 14. So that's going to be the
same for the velocity function. All we
need to find is the maximum velocity. So
let's go ahead and do that.
Now vax
is equal to the square roo of k / m
* a. We know that the amplitude is the
number in front of cosine, which is 1.5.
We know the mass. It's 0.55.
The only thing that we're missing is the
spring constant K which we can use this
equation 2 p^ 2 * the mass. So we got to
find the frequency
12.4t is equal to 2 pi ft which means
that 2 pi f is 12.4.
So therefore the frequency
is 12.4 / 2 pi.
Well actually we really don't need to
find a frequency. What we could do is
simply replace 2 pi f with 12.4
since we have 2 pi f in the equation. So
2 pi f is going to be 12.4 and then
we're going to square it and multiply by
0.55.
So the spring constant is 84.568.
So with that information
we can now find vmax.
So that's going to be the square t of k
which is 84.568
/ m which is 0.55 * the amplitude of
1.5.
So 84.568
/ 55 that's 153.76
and the square root of that is 12.4 *
1.5.
Therefore the maximum velocity is 18.6 6
m/s.
So the equation of the velocity as a
function of time it's negative
18.6 sign
and this part is just 12.4. So sine
12.4t.
Now let's find the acceleration
function. So we got to find the maximum
acceleration first.
And the maximum acceleration
is equal to
K * A / M.
So K
is 84.568.
The amplitude is 1.5 and the mass is 0
55.
Therefore, the maximum acceleration is
230.64.
The equation for the acceleration as a
function of time it's equal to the
negative
maximum acceleration
time cossine
2 pi ft.
So that's going to be 230.64 64 cossine
12.4
t.
So if you have the position function,
it's not that difficult to write the
velocity function and the acceleration
function. You need to know the generic
equation. This part is going to stay the
same and you need to know the equations
to find the maximum velocity and the
maximum acceleration.
So now let's work on the next part.
Let's find the velocity.5
m from its equilibrium position. So
using the equation that we have v of t
is equal to -8.6
sin
12.4t.
So we're looking for V of.5.
So that's -8.6
sine 12.4 *.5 that's going to be 6.2.
So make sure the calculator is in uh
radian mode for this to work. Sine of
6.2 in radian mode is about.083.
And if we multiply that by8.6 six. The
velocity at this point it's 1.545
m/s.
So now let's find the acceleration. So
let's write the function first. It's
-230.64
cosine
12.4t.
So this is going to be cosine 6.2 Just
like
sin 6.2 cossine 6.2 is about.9965
multiplied by -230.64.
The acceleration at this point is
-229.84
m/s squared. Now that we have the
acceleration, we can calculate the
restoring force.
So the restoring force is simply going
to be the mass times the acceleration.
So the mass is 0.55 and the acceleration
-229.84.
So the restoring force at this point is
about -126.4
newtons.
So that is it for this problem.
A spring of force constant 300 newtons
per meter vibrates with an amplitude of
45 cm when a.35 kg mass hangs from it.
What is the equation describing this
motion? If the mass passes through the
equilibrium point with positive velocity
at t=0.
So we have a vertical spring. We have a
mass hanging from it.
Now there's four points at which there's
four ways that the system can start.
It can start above
the equilibrium position
in which case it has no choice but to go
downward. So at t equals z for this
particular shape or this particular
situation it has negative velocity
because it's going in the negative y
direction.
So therefore to graph it it is starting
at the top
with an amplitude of positive a.
So this would be the cosine graph
positive cosine to be exact. So x would
be equal to positive
a cosine
2 pi ft.
But we don't have that situation.
This is if it's starting above the
equilibrium point and if it's going down
with negative velocity at t equals z.
The situation that we have for part A
is that it's starting at the equilibrium
position
and it's moving with positive velocity.
That means it's going this way
in the positive y direction. So to graph
it, because it's at the equilibrium
point, it starts at the center and it's
going in a positive y direction. So it's
going to go up.
This graph is positive sign. So the
position function is going to equal
positive a
sin 2 pi ft.
So that's what we have for part a. But
let's say if part A was different. Let's
say if everything was the same. The mass
passes through the equilibrium point but
with negative velocity meaning that it's
going in a downward direction. I'm going
to graph it in blue. So in that case it
starts at the equilibrium position that
is the origin but it's going down and
then up. So the ne the blue sign wave
would represent this function. Instead
of being positive sign, it's going to be
negative a sin 2 pi ft. If it was going
in the negative y direction.
So anytime it starts at the equilibrium
position, use the sign function. If it
goes up, use positive sign. If it's
going down from the equilibrium point,
use negative sign. So let's get back to
the the stuff that we're trying to
figure out which is positive a sin 2 pi
ft.
So we have the amplitude it's 45 cm
which is45 m.
Now what we need to figure out is 2 pi
f.
We know that k is equal to 2 f^ 2 *
m.
So k / m is 2 pi f^2. So 2 pi f is the
square root of k m.
K is 300. The mass is.35.
300 /.35
is 857.1.
If you take the square root of that, you
should get 29.28
or 29.3.
Therefore the position function is going
to be a which is uh
time sin 2 pi f which is 29.28
* t
and this is positive.45.
Now what about the second part of the
question? What if the mass starts at the
lowest point below the equilibrium
point?
So let's say this is the equilibrium
point. If it starts below it, it has no
choice but to go up. It can't go down if
it's at the lowest point. So it has to
be moving up with positive velocity.
So if we graph it,
we're starting at a. So if you don't
start at the center, it's going to be
the cosine function. S always starts at
the center. Since we're starting at the
bottom, this is negative cosine. So x is
a cosine 2 pi ft. So the equation that
describes this motion is.45
cosine 29.28
* t. So that's the answer for part B.
So let's review.
There's four functions that you need to
know.
So it can start at the equilibrium
position and go up with positive
velocity or it can go down with negative
velocity starting from the equilibrium
position or it could start from the top
or it could start from the bottom.
Anytime it starts from the center,
you have the positive sign function. If
it's going up, if it starts from the
center and goes down, it's negative
sign.
If it starts at the top, it's positive
cosine. If it starts at the bottom,
negative cosine. And remember, the
origin represents the equilibrium
position.
Now, let's talk about damp harmonic
motion. This form of motion occurs when
friction is present.
But let's draw two graphs. When friction
is not present and when it is present.
So let's say this is positive a
and negative a.
And let's say the graph starts at the
top. The mass is pulled to the right and
then released from rest. So there's no
friction
the amplitude will be constant.
The energy in the system remains the
same. Notice that the amplitude is not
decreasing.
That is the maximum amplitude
or the maximum displacement.
Now what if friction is present?
How will that change the appearance of
the graph?
So if friction is present,
it's going to lose
energy and so the amplitude is going to
decrease over time
until eventually it reaches zero.
In this case, dampen has occurred.
So dampen is caused by friction. It
could be internal friction or friction
due to air molecules,
but it reduces the energy of the system
and this is seen by a decrease in
amplitude over time.
Now, there's three different types of
dampen that you need to be familiar
with.
There's overdampen, under dampen, and
critical dampen.
When the system is under damp,
the object
will make a few swings before it comes
to rest.
So, it's going to make a few cycles and
eventually it's going to become zero.
Now, if it's over damp,
it won't get the chance to make multiple
cycles.
Within its first cycle, it's going to
lose all of its energy
and go to zero, but it's going to take a
long time for it to do that. And then
there's critical dampen
where it reaches zero faster and it
doesn't make multiple cycles.
Critical dampening is useful for the
shock absorbers in a car. You don't want
your car bouncing up and down every time
it hits a bump. You want it to absorb
that energy fast. And so you want
critical dampening in a situation where
you have an underdamp uh system.
Let's say like a a door that's old. It
can bounce back and forth before it
closes. And you don't want that.
So whenever you want to reduce bouncing
in a device, you want critical
dampening. You want to remove the energy
as quickly as possible
from the system.
Now there's one other topic that we need
to discuss and that is resonant
frequency.
When you apply a force to an oscillator,
you can cause forced vibrations to occur
and as you force the oscillator to move,
you can increase the amplitude. However,
if you apply the force at the natural
frequency of the object, it's going to
be most effective when increasing the
amplitude.
So if the applied frequency
matches the natural frequency or if it's
very close to it,
the amplitude
can increase greatly.
When the applied frequency matches the
natural frequency, it's known as the
resonant frequency.
A good example to illustrate this is a
swing. Imagine if you have a child on a
swing
and
to increase the amplitude of the swing,
you need to push the child at the right
position
and that is while the child is swinging
back towards you. That's when you apply
the push and at that point the child can
go higher and higher. However, let's say
if you try to push the child at the
middle at the equilibrium position,
you probably will not get the greatest
effects and increase in the amplitude.
You want to apply the force
at a rate that's equal to the natural
frequency. If you do that, then the
applied force is at the resonant
frequency and that's when you can
achieve maximum amplitude. That's when
you can increase the amplitude of the
oscillator most effectively.
So just make sure that you keep this
fact in mind. Whenever the applied force
matches the natural frequency of the
system that is the resonant frequency,
the applied force will be most effective
in increasing the amplitude of the
oscillator.